<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the anniversary meeting of the natives of St. Martins in the Fields, at their own parochial church, on May 29, 1684 by Richard Burd, A.M., chaplain to the Right Honourable the Lord President, and lecturer of St. Mary Aldermanbury ; published at the request of the stewards.</title>
            <author>Burd, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5616</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34772</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14699638</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14699638</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1566:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the anniversary meeting of the natives of St. Martins in the Fields, at their own parochial church, on May 29, 1684 by Richard Burd, A.M., chaplain to the Right Honourable the Lord President, and lecturer of St. Mary Aldermanbury ; published at the request of the stewards.</title>
                  <author>Burd, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Keble ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved illustration on t.p. verso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Restoration, 1660-1688 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102700:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the <hi>ANNIVERSARY MEETING</hi> OF THE NATIVES OF St. <hi>MARTINS</hi> in the Fields At their Own Parochial Church, on <hi>May</hi> 29. 1684.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>RICHARD B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RD,</hi> A. M. Chaplain to the Right Honourable the Lord Preſident, and Lecturer of St. <hi>Mary Aldermanbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the requeſt of the Stewards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Keble</hi> at the <hi>Turks-Head</hi> over againſt <hi>Fetter-Lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:102700:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:102700:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102700:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102700:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON <hi>Preached</hi> May 29th. 1684. ON
<q>
                  <bibl>St. <hi>Matt. 21.42:</hi>
                  </bibl> — The Stone which the Builders rejected, the ſame is become the Head of the corner.</q>
            </head>
            <p>BY the Stone, which was here diſcarded and thrown aſide, is certainly typified and prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the rejection of our bleſſed Saviour, the caſting off and renouncing of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> who was ſent into the world <hi>to be a light unto the</hi> Gentiles, <hi>and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102700:4"/>to be the glory of the people</hi> Iſrael. And <hi>the Builders,</hi> that thus deſpiſed his domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and rule over them, were the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> thoſe hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal and Sanctimonious Zealots, who all along moſt deſpitefully treated him, and at length glutted their malice and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge by putting him to death. And after all his deep humility, rejection, and ſufferings, God raiſed him from the dead, advanced him to his Kingdom at his own right hand, and ſo made him, tho once <hi>a ſtone rejected by the builders,</hi> the chief and <hi>Head of the Corner,</hi> uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> into one Spiritual-building. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> proves as much in the audience of many thouſands of the <hi>Jews, Nemine contradicente.</hi> Acts 4.11. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>whom ye crucified, this is the ſtone that was ſet at nought of you builders, which is now exalted into Heaven,</hi> and become Head of the Church as well Triumpant as Militant here upon Earth.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:102700:4"/>
            <p> So that the Text as it is legible in the Goſpels, undoubtedly points at the Crucifixion of the <hi>Meſſias</hi> by the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees.</hi> But if we turn to the 118. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> whence the words are quoted, than they may refer to the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> himſelf, and the Jewiſh Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins univerſally ſo applied them, and that with good ſeaſon, provided the Pſalm be interpreted only as a ſong of thankſgiving and not as a Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; for it exactly, correſponds to the condition and circumſtances of <hi>David,</hi> who had been long exerciſed with many potent enemies and afflictions on every ſide; and had been oppoſed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected by the Houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the Chieftains of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in reference to his Kingdom; and had lain for ſome time under proſcription and baniſhment: Yet God at length ſtood up in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, hearing him in all his troubles, redreſſing his grievances, helping him to ſubdue and diſcomfit all the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102700:5"/>hoſts of his enemies; and maugre all difficulties and oppoſitions bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him back from exile, and eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing him on the Throne of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom over <hi>Iſrael</hi> as well as <hi>Judah;</hi> making him (tho at firſt a <hi>ſtone rejected by the builders,</hi> yet at laſt) <hi>Head of the corner.</hi> Then did holy <hi>David</hi> pen this Pſalm as tis conjectur'd, and afterwards Hymn it in the praiſe and glorification of God.</p>
            <p>And, as I doubt not but all the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Hearts of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> did congratulate <hi>David,</hi> when he enter'd into the Royal City; and afterwards went into the Sanctuary to offer up unto God their ſacrifice of praiſe and thankſgivings for returning their King home again. So now, let every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of this Loyal Aſſembly, according to the deſign and occaſion of this ſolem Anniverſary Feſtival, pour out in the preſence of God, all imaginable praiſe and glory for a deliverance, as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102700:5"/>ſtupendious and amazing for <hi>number, weight and meaſure,</hi> as ever God in his wiſe Providence diſpenſed unto the men of <hi>Judah,</hi> or any other people ſince the inchoation of the world.</p>
            <p>I appeal to the Chronicles of the moſt early times, and challenge all Regiſters of whatſoever Age to inſtance in any Kingdom or Republick, that has been reduced to ſo low an ebb, to ſuch ſad extremities, and ſo perfectly unable to emerge from the calamity: That were of ſuch implacable enmities and diſcord within themſelves, and ſo mortally curſed and hated by all neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Provinces: and at laſt to be ſo miraculouſly redeemed out of every ſtraight and difficulty; and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leſt drop of blood, to the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable joy of all our hearts and the amazement of all about us; and at a time, when no Soul alive could ever hope for or imagin ſuch a ſudden and proſperous turn of affairs in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102700:6"/>
            <p> We were along time like the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> a grievous and afflicted people; and had our Country depopulated by the inroads of mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and imperious Tyrants; its ſtrength and ſinews enervated by civil and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine broils; our rights and liberties all infringed; our eſtates and fortunes confiſcated; our lives expoſed to inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable hazards; whole families extinct and buried in ruins; the State and Government quite inverted and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; all order and peacediſſolved and broken up; the Scepter and Royal Throne uſurp'd; the late King, of ever bleſſed memory executed at his own door; his Sons and all the Royal Line proſcribed out of the Kingdom; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of the prime Nobility haſtily diſpatch'd to attend the Funerals of their Royal Maſter; and thouſands of other inferiour Subjects Eccleſiaſtical as well as Civil, had all their necks cruſh'd to peices by the Chariot-wheels
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102700:6"/>of inſulting <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Yea Gods <hi>holy Vineyard</hi> too miſerably laid waſt and troden under foot, and that very Church, which was once ſo remarkable for its Orthodox faith, good diſcipline, whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Canons, modeſt and decent way of worſhip, all brought to nought; and nothing but looſe Doctrines and moſt damnable hereſies ſucceeding in the room of them.</p>
            <p>To ſuch an amazing height of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and confuſion was this Nation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, and ſuch as this was our lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſtate and condition!</p>
            <p>And after thoſe many attempts that were made, and all honeſt and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minds had ſtrove their utmoſt to ſtop this impetuous torrent and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treive their Country from ſuch a Sea of miſeries: when there was no hopes left, and the Nation juſt a ſinking under its own burden: When <hi>the waters had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt drowned us and the ſtreams had gone e'ne over our Souls:</hi> Then did the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102700:7"/>lift up his voice out of the deep, and the floods ſtrait obeyed and drive back again; then did God ſpeak peace to this Britiſh Iſland, and wrought our delivery in a trice, infatuating all the Counſels of the Mighty, undermining all their projects and ſecret Machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſtrangely ſcattering all the bands and Militia of the Nation; and by an extraordinary act of grace and mercy, above our hopes, and beyond our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and with wonderful eaſe and ſafety, reſtoring our moſt gracious Soveraign to all his Kingdoms, and his Loving Subjects to their juſt rights and liberties; and withal bringing the <hi>Ark</hi> and our Religion home again, and eſtabliſhing it on the ſame baſis, with all its Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal conſtitutions; together with a profound peace and plenty, and an univerſal joy, and gladſomeneſs on every brow accompanying the return of ſo indulgent and merciful a Prince, even to the vileſt and moſt profligate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:102700:7"/>his people; who, though he had been long diſcarded and lain aſide, yet, you ſee, God on this <hi>day</hi> ſat him on the Royal throne of his Fathers, and ſo the words of my Text are again made out.</p>
            <p>That very <hi>ſtone, which the builders rejected the ſame</hi> now, bleſſed be God, <hi>is head</hi> over <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſin, which the Builders here in the Text were guilty of, was open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and diſloyalty to our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, reſolving that he ſhould have no rule or Kingſhip over them, and that made them diſcard and lay him aſide.</p>
            <p>Now this is ſtill the ſame reigning iniquity, that was the occaſion and commencement of our late unhappy broils, and which broke up the ſluces, and cauſed all the forementioned, and much worſe evils to guſh in upon us.</p>
            <p>And therefore, that I may keep cloſe to my Text, and anſwer the end for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102700:8"/>which I am appointed; and ſeeing the day alſo does ſo neceſſarily determine me to it, give me leave to ſhew you, firſt, the duty of Subjects to their Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, to tell you wherein it conſiſts: Secondly, I will uſe two or three argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to preſs you to a conſciencious diſcharge of it, that we may all practice it better for the time to come, and ſtudy no more to <hi>reject</hi> and throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide <hi>the head ſtone of the corner:</hi> Than thirdly and laſtly, I will give ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and ſhort reflexions upon the day, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>Begin we now with the firſt, to ſhow you wherein the duty of ſubjects to their governours conſiſts; And among ſeveral branches that might be named I ſhall at preſent only ſpeak to theſe four following.</p>
            <p>The firſt branch of our duty to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours is, to honour and reverence their ſacred Perſons.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102700:8"/>
            <p> Sayes the Apoſtle, <hi>fear God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17.</note> 
               <hi>honour the King.</hi> He gives us our duty to both in the ſame breath; and the reaſon why ſuch great obeyſance and humility ought to be paid to the perſon of the King is, <hi>becauſe he is Gods repreſentative upon Earth.</hi> So that Kings and Princes muſt be lookt upon, as upon them, on whom God hath ſtampt much of his own power and Authority, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought to pay all honour and eſteem, never daring upon any pretence whatſoever <hi>to ſpeak evil of the ruler of our people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 23.5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Nay! they that deſpiſe and ſet light by Princes, refuſing the homage that is due unto them, expreſly ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>fifth Commandment,</hi> which obliges us to honour our parents, And the Magiſtrate is the Civil parent of all thoſe that are under his dominion and Royalty; And the name is well deſerved, becauſe he takes care of our lives, defends us from all dangers, wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102700:9"/>and ſuperintends over us for our good, and ſo makes his Government a publick and univerſal bleſſing to the Nation; And thoſe, which refuſe to honour the <hi>Civil Parent,</hi> do openly confront and violate one of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of <hi>the ſecond table.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Add to this, the baſe ingratitude that ſuch men muſt needs be guilty of, that can find in their hearts thus to ſlight and contemn them after all the care and pains they have taken for their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity and well-being. <hi>Lycurgus</hi> the great Law-maker, when he had allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted puniſhments to moſt vices, was asked why he had made no Law againſt the ſin of ingratitude, and his anſwer was, that's <hi>res prodigioſa,</hi> a thing ſo monſtrouſly wicked and abſurd that no body in his wits can be guilty of it: And ſurely it muſt be ingratitude with a witneſs to deny honour and deference to thoſe, by whoſe wiſe conduct and Government we owe e'ne our lives, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102700:9"/>liberties, Religion, and what not.</p>
            <p>Let us all then like dutyful and Loyal ſubjects pay obeyſance unto our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and have a profound and aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful reverence for their Perſonages, and eſteem them ſacred, in as much as they are Gods Deputies and Viceroys, whom next under himſelf he hath intruſted with the care and adminiſtration of his people. Should an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, as ſoon as he is come aſhore, be abuſed and ſet at nought, the indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty does not terminate here, but lies up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Prince which ſent him, and who no doubt will avenge the wrong that is done him in the perſon of his Miniſter? or ſuppoſe a man ſhould have his Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture ſtabbed through with a Sword, or a limb of it cut off, has he not great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to reſent the injury as done to his own perſon, and ſtudy a puniſhment ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly? Why thus will God do to all thoſe that affront the <hi>Supream Powers,</hi> they being his Ambaſſadours and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legates,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102700:10"/>and ſerve as ſo many pictures and images to repreſent Gods great power and Soveraignty over his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Nay! God has given to Kings and Princes his own Auguſt and venerable name — <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods</hi> — And in the 1 <hi>Chron.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6.</note> the Throne, which they ſat upon, is ſtyled <hi>Gods throne</hi> — where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing God himſelf has ſo highly Dignified them, as to ſet them on his Throne, and to call them after his own name, it is much more becoming all their ſubjects to keep their diſtance and pay homage before them, and to have an inward worſhip and eſteem for them, which muſt be expreſſed by our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mean and deportment, by humble and lowly proſtrations, by a chearful and ready compliance with their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and that conſtantly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly, without partiality or hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſie, having no by or ſiniſter ends of our own, but doing it in great ſincerity
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102700:10"/>and truth. What a reverend Author<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quotes and applies upon another occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I may, with ſmall alteration uſe to this. Saith he, <q>'Tis a remarkable paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that <hi>Aelian</hi> the Hiſtorian gives of a proud man, who being to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the preſence of the <hi>Perſian</hi> King, before whom he muſt make ſuch ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as he had no mind to give, he therefore let fall his Ring at his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the preſence-Chamber, and his ſtooping to take that up, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for a worſhip of that great Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty. So many perſons ſeem outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to worſhip their Prince, and make very humble and lowly addreſſes unto him, when indeed they do but ſtoop to their own intereſt, and are but tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſome Court preferment, which they have more mind to than to be humble and Loyal.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly another branch of our duty to Governours is cuſtome and tribute. We muſt pay them tribute.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:102700:11"/>
            <p> And this we are obliged to perform by the example of our bleſſed Saviour, who, when the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Herodians</hi> asked him whether <hi>it was lawful to pay Tribute or not,</hi> he anſwer'd their Captious queſtion, as his uſual manner was, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting another; ſaying, <hi>whoſe Image and ſuperſcription is this? Why</hi> Caeſars. <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der therefore unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſars — And at another time when Chriſt was taxed and no Money to pay, rather then he would be thought refractory, he wrought a Miracle to pay his aſſeſsment.</p>
            <p>Nay!
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.28.</note> the Apoſtles afterwards, whoſe Epiſtles are only a comment upon our Savious ſayings, acknowledges this. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> eſpecially counſels the Romans to <hi>render to all their dues, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to whom tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom, Fear to whom fear, Honour to whom Honour;</hi> and a little higher he aſſigns the reaſon why they muſt pay them Tribute, becauſe <hi>they are Gods
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102700:11"/>Miniſtersattending continually upon this very thing i. e.;</hi> for the ſafegard and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of his people.</p>
            <p>God hath ſet them a part as his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents for the good of the people, and 'tis highly reaſonable they ſhould be maintained and ſupported by them. And indeed when it is conſidered what are the cares and troubles of that high calling? How many thorns are platted in every Crown? We ſhall have but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cauſe to envy them, or retrench their dues. Men generally admire the ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power and authority of Princes, the high honours and dignities, the vaſt revenues and exchequers, but never conſider the inſuperable hazards and perils, and what abundance of plots and conſpiracies, rolling haſtily, like the Waves of the Sea, one upon the neck of another, which are continually de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed againſt them. They look upon one ſide of the Medal and there ſee a fair Image and inſcription, but ne're
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102700:12"/>turn the reverſe and behold the croſſes and bars that are on the other. <hi>Tully</hi> ſomewhere in his Offices, tells us when <hi>Democles</hi> the great Paraſite was arrayed like a Prince, and ſat at a Table where there was a rich banquet provided for him; as ſoon as ever he ſaw the naked ſword, with the point downward, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging juſt over his head, he could not for his life taſte of his entertainment, or take any comfort in the Royal atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance he had. By which ingenious em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem <hi>Cicero</hi> ſhews, that the life of a King, in the midſt of all his pomp and grandeur, is in continual fear of Death. Wherefore let no man deny him his juſt tribute or ſubſidy, ſince he earns it dear enough in all conſcience, when we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon the many eares and diſquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes; the ſudden frights and dangers his Sacred perſon is daily expoſed to.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, another branch of our duty to Governours is this, we muſt daily put up our prayers to God for them.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:102700:12"/>
            <p> This alſo is laid down by the Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>I exhort therefore firſt of all, that ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Prayers, and interceſſions, and giving of thanks, be made for all men, for Kings and all that are in authority un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, that we may all lead a quiet and peaceable life in all godlineſs and honeſty;</hi> and the prayers which are thus put up for the preſervation of the King, and all that are in commiſſion under him, will wheel about and ſoon recoil into our own boſoms, becauſe the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, which they receive from God, and which we ought conſtantly to pray for, tends to the good of the people, that every man may happily enjoy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>and eat the fruit of his Labour under his own Vine, and under his own Fig-tree.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore if we had no Love for our Governours or our Country, yet for our own ſakes and the intereſt of our ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral friends and relations, it concerns us to ſupplicate heaven in their behalf, that they may be our ſtrength and fortreſs
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102700:13"/>our defence and Buckler in time of need; that God would ſo rule their hearts, and ſtrengthen their hands, that they may neither want will nor power to puniſh wickedneſs and vice, and to maintain Gods true Religion and virtue; that they may all give us wiſe and whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Laws for the retrenching our exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitances and the government of our lives, for the bridling our unruly wills and affections, and to get the maſtery over our paſſions, and to fright us by ſevere penalties from the perpetration of every thing that is evil and ſinful: And ſure I am that many of us are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding more to the good government we live under, then to our own princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for being ſuch as we are; for if the Laws of the Land did not tye men up, and make it death to commit Murder, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin, or Robbery, I am confident men would as frequently be found culpable herein, as in Swearing, Drunkenneſs, Fornication, Prophaning the Sabbath,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102700:13"/>and the like. And therefore we have all great reaſon to uphold the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and to pray for our Senators, and to bleſs and praiſe God night and day for putting it into their hearts for provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thus for our Souls as well as our bodies, for publiſhing ſuch gracious edicts, and conſtituting ſuch eaſie and gentle Laws, Which ought to be the pride and glory of the Engliſh ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>It is ſtoried of the people in <hi>China,</hi> that if any of them have a mind to travel abroad and ſet but one foot out of their own Country, they muſt never return home again; and was there not great policy in the Magiſtrates for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgating ſuch a decree? for if once the Chineſſes ſhould venture to go out and behold what great liberty other Countries enjoy above what they do in their own, there would quickly be not a man left for the Governours to rule over. But thanks be to God, our caſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102700:14"/>is widely diſtant from other Countries, and no people ever enjoyed a more relax and gentle Government, where the reins are in a manner flung upon the necks of the Subjects; and all its laws are calculated ſolely for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and eaſe, for the intereſt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, for the ſafegard of our ſouls as well as our bodies: and never earth bore a more gracious Prince, a more indulgent and merciful Soveraign than weilds the Scepter in theſe Kingdoms; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have all the reaſon in the world to ſupplicate and interceed with God for the preſervation of his Majeſties moſt Sacred perſon, and the Government as it is by Law eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>But fourthly, the laſt branch of our duty to Governours is this, entirely to reſign our ſelves into their hands and ſubmit to their good will and pleaſure in all things. Now becauſe this part of our duty is moſt ſcrupled at, and a great deal worſe practiced by us, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102700:14"/>carefully conſider it by it ſelf, and with that freedom and plainneſs as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the place where I now ſtand, and uſe but theſe three arguments to engage your performance of it. And afterwards I will haſten to a concluſion of the whole.</p>
            <p>My firſt Topick is this, obedience and ſubjection to Magiſtrates is one of the eſſential marks of our Chriſtian profeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Primitive Saint,</hi> in the infancy of the Church, was alwaies better known by his Catholick charity, and patient ſubmiſſion to perſecuting Emperors than by all the other graces in the whole Syſtom of Divinity: It was the undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> and beſt diſtinguiſhing note, whereby you might judge infallibly of the profeſſours of chriſtianity from any others whatever; becauſe no other religion enjoyns ſuch an exact obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the commands of our gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. this is ſtrictly charged by saint
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102700:15"/>
               <hi>Peter, Submit your ſelves to every ordin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supream or unto Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours as thoſe that are ſent by him for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in the 13th. to the <hi>Romans</hi> is moſt full to this purpoſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 1. <hi>Verſe</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers — And whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God, and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves damnation:</hi> And than concludes, <hi>wherefore ye muſt needs be ſubject not only for fear but alſo for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake,</hi> out of a ſenſe that it is a duty which God exacts at our hands. And tis very obſervable, that theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts were all given at a time when thoſe powers were Roman Emperours, and cruel perſecutors of Chriſtianity, to ſhew that no <hi>pretence of the wickedneſs of our Rulers can exempt us from this duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay! in the caſe of our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and if ever reſiſtance would be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102700:15"/>tolerated and indulg'd, one might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it in this; And yet Chriſt would not allow of it, but ſharply rebuked <hi>Peter</hi> for drawing out his ſword and ſmiting one of the inferiour officers, ſaying, <hi>they that take the Sword ſhall periſh by the Sword:</hi> And ſome learned men are of the opinion, that the <hi>Souldiers</hi> which came to ſeize him had no war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant but was rather a rabble that broke out <hi>with ſwords and ſtaves</hi> of their own accord and motion; and yet Chriſt was ſo jealous of infringing the ſupream authority, that he would not notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſuffer any oppoſition to be made.</p>
            <p>By the holy inſtitutes and exemplar of our Saviour and his Apoſtles, we muſt all pay obedience unto our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, either active or paſſive; active in the caſe of all lawful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, and paſſive when the thing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned is repugnant to the letter of Scripture: herein, I confeſs, we are not bound to act as they would have us;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102700:16"/>but even this is a ſeaſon for paſſive o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and we ought quietly to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo whatſoever is inflicted for ſuch a refuſal, and not to ſecure our ſelves and riſe up againſt them. Nay! it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten happens out that worſe evils and more bloodſhed will follow reſiſtance than by patiently ſuffering; as hath been happily obſerved by ſome Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians that how bloody ſoever <hi>Nero</hi> was, yet there was not ſo much blood ſpilt in his fourteen years reign as there was within a few months after his death. Wherefore men had better patiently ſubmit their necks to the Yoke, than to riſe up and rebel, and ſo derive down greater judgments upon their own heads.</p>
            <p>I am ſufficiently ſenſible, this is a very irkſon doctrine to carnal and worldly minded people, to the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of fleſh and blood, and yet this is no more than what Chriſtianity obliges us to, if ever we hope for ſalvation; and which the <hi>planters and propagaters</hi> of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102700:16"/>our Religion all ſtuck to and died by it. But alas there is no ſuch danger and trials now, as there was in thoſe days, before Chriſtianity was adopted into the Laws of the Empire; we have no perſecution raiſed againſt the Church, but we all live in Luxury and eaſe, as for what has been lately uſed againſt Diſſenters, ought not in any wiſe to be branded with ſo foul a character, theſe are not perſecutions but light and gentle admonitions only, full of affectionate care and kindneſs, ſent to mind them of their duty to their Mother, and to joyn in communion with that Church, out of the Pale whereof Salvation can hardly be obtained. The <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> were ſo paſſionately concerned when a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one forſook their Schools, that they preſently carried out a Coffin after him, and ſo gave him over for a loſt and dead man. And how I pray ſhall thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us be reckoned in a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, who nere come near our aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies but refuſe canonical obedience and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102700:17"/>deſpiſe the Sacred ſtanding Ordinances of the Church, which are the very life and nouriſhment of all its members: The meer ſuſpenſion and deprivation whereof was that which made the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Excommunicants, as they lay weeping and condoling before the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, ſo importunately to requeſt the prayers and interceſſions of all good Chriſtians, when they entered the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, for a plenary indulgence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> abſolution of all their ſins, that they might again be admitted into a fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with the Church, out of which no ſpiritual gift or bleſſing can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, and 'tis for this end only that our Rulers ſtudy now to bring ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us within the Pale, they are wiſe Senators, and know what is beſt, and are kinder to them than they are to themſelves, and therefore they ſhake the rod over them, being ſolicitous to ſcare and draw them to the conſtant frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the publick Oratories, which is of ſuch infinite concern to the everlaſting
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:102700:17"/>welfare of their ſouls; and this is all the ſeverity that is exerciſed towards them, and how can any ſhorter courſe be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and what gentler lenatives can be applied to make them come in than this.</p>
            <p>But nevertheleſs, there is a loud out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry made and a great talk of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and much muttering and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in our Streets, and never more ſymptoms of Rebellion and diſloyalty than now; and which is moſt ſtrange, from thoſe that call themſelves Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans? but how does it appear that they are ſuch, if they dont diſcover better principles? We ſhall never find then out unleſs their actions be ſuitable to their their profesſion, and therefore if they would be known they muſt be ſerved as an unskilful painter does all his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, when no eye can diſcover by the features and Lineaments whom they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent, he is forced to ſubſcribe their names; ſo muſt theſe men have the name of Chriſt Stampt upon their fore head
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:102700:18"/>or elſe by their practiſes we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know them; for Rebellion and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience is diametrically oppoſite to the inſtitutes of Chriſtianity, and I have read that it is a mark to diſcover Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans by, but never Chriſtians before.</p>
            <p>Secondly, another argument I draw from the danger of its contrary, which is this, that diſobedience unto Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours is as mortal and damning a ſin as any of thoſe that more immediately concerns the honour of God.</p>
            <p>God holds the Balance even and bears an equal regard to all his ſanctions, and threatens no greater penalty for the breach of one than another, but Wills our obedience to Governours as much as to himſelf. God makes no difference, but looks upon every ſin with the ſame abhorrency, and albeit he ſeems in Scripture to be more ſevere with the Jews for the ſin of Idolatry, yet this was only to put them farther off from it, that being the firſt Religion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:102700:18"/>of their Country, and to which they was moſt prone; and not but God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all kind of vices alike, and tho ſome be of a deeper tincture than others, yet <hi>the Wages of every ſin is death;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23.</note>
            </p>
            <p>God therefore lays no greater ſtreſs upon one precept than another, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth us to all his commands impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and calls for our performance of thoſe duties to our Neighbour, and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral relations we ſtandinone to another, as much as thoſe that more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern his own worſhip. Nay! he is ſometimes pleaſed to diſpenſe with the non performance of his own Laws, but never thoſe that relate to the good and benefit of mankind.</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding the Scribes and Phariſees of old had a mind to be more civil to God than he would have them, and were reſolved to give his Laws the preeminence, and ne're matter all the other commandments, ſo they did but obſerve what belonged to the ſervice of God; and therefore they ſtood up migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:102700:19"/>for his Worſhip and Glory, and were ſtrict obſervers of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry zealous in defence of their Religion, and cryed up every where <hi>the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord,</hi> and all the while neglected every other duty of equal moment and concern, lived in open rebellion to their Rulers, proved annoyance to the ſtate, had no bowels of mercy and compasſion, but <hi>devoured Widows houſes,</hi> and were greatly injurious to their Neighbours intereſt.</p>
            <p>And I am afraid we have many ſuch now a days, who are great Champions for the Church, and are very forward to maintain the cauſe of God, and think themſelves highly obliged to obſerve his Laws and Ordinances, but ne're mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how negligent and remiſs they are of others: Who take great care to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge their duty of <hi>the firſt table,</hi> and yet can freely indulge themſelves in a manifeſt violation of thoſe of <hi>the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond;</hi> as if Religion was deſigned to be a <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> to common honeſty,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:102700:19"/>and if we did but often invoke God in our prayers, we might afterwards go lye, cheat, and abuſe our neighbour. I have the charity to believe that many of them are not given to prophane the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> to curſing or ſwearing, to drunkenneſs or fornication, nor to any ſuch groſs and ſenſual immoralities, but none more guilty of Spiritual and Phariſaical vices than they; there are none ſo proud and cenforious, ſo covetous and worldly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo falſe and hypocritical, ſo facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſeditious, and ſo diſobedient unto Princes and Governours as they are. And if theſe be not mortal and damning ſins what are? and yet all this is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be done out of pure zeal to God and Religion: but if we trace out the firſt Authors and abettor of this ſurious and miſguided zeal, we ſhall quickly find them to be the Jeſuits. For there is no footſteps of this in the records of very early times, but juſt upon the breaking out of the Reformation then this active fiery zeal began firſt to blaze, and kindle, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:102700:20"/>embroil the whole nation out of zeal to their Idolatrous rites and ceremonies: and before our Iſland could be throughly purged from all the Jeſuits and Seminary Prieſts that ſwarmed amongſt us, they they rubbed their leprofie upon ſome of our honeſt Country men, and e'ne left the infection behind them. So that this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent zeal for Religion was an old Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Church engin, tho now moved about and played by other hands. And this <hi>Andreas Ab Haberfeild</hi> in his Letter to Sir <hi>William Boſewell</hi> plainly declares.</p>
            <p>But thirdly and laſtly, whether we will be obedient to our Governours or not, yet God will have his ends ſerved in the world.</p>
            <p>Sayes <hi>Solomon, there are many devices in the heart of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.21.</note> 
               <hi>nevertheleſs the Counſel of the Lord that ſhall ſtand.</hi> How void of ſenſe and reaſon is it then, for ſuch mortal creatures as we are to pretend to have our wills fulfilled before Gods, and to order all things in the world as we would have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:102700:20"/>them? are we able to baffle the counſels and purpoſes of the Almighty, or to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and change the courſe of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence? can we cancel the ſacred ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Heaven, and make the everlaſting decrees of none effect? no! the divine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments muſt ſtand for ever, and are fixed and unalterable as the center of the earth; and what from all eternity was preordained muſt ſo happen out and come to paſs, tho it be never ſo contrariant to the humors and fancies of unquiet men. Why then will any interpoſe and grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the Almighty, turn Rebels and affront his Viceroys and ſtudy to diſmount thoſe whom he hath appointed to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us? if God ſhould ſuſpend his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence and ſuffer Rebellion to ride tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant and grow proſperous, yet alas it is but for a while, and then the Scene changes, and a new face of things ſtrait ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears: So that altho God may a little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtinate and adjourn the execution of his deſigns, yet they ſhall take place, when he ſees it fitting and convenient, and then
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:102700:21"/>muſt all Rebels be debaſed and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and them that ſhould preſide over us again exalted.</p>
            <p>Wherefore let this rally up the Spirits of every wiſe and Religious Prince; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is a God above, who beholds all the ſtruglings of their enemies, and and knows how hard they bare againſt the curb, and fain would trample them underfoot. And altho the affairs of their Kingdoms may be ſometimes in a ſad plight, and look towards a change. Yet God can work miracles, and make the wind tack about, and in an inſtant reſcue them out of every ſtraight and difficulty. Who could have thought, when <hi>Joſeph</hi> was betrayed by his Bretheren and fold into <hi>Aegypt</hi> a ſlave, ſhould at laſt be Lord over <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſehold? When <hi>Jonas</hi> was caſt into the Sea and ſwallowed up by a Whale, to have met him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards preaching at <hi>Nineveh?</hi> When <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezar,</hi> was grazing in the foreſt among the Beaſts, to ſee him again govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Babel?</hi> When the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo totally
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:102700:21"/>routed by the Chaldees, who ſackt Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, burnt their Temple, and carried them Captive into <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſhould at laſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored and ſet at liberty by that heathen <hi>Perſian Monarch Cyrus?</hi> When that ſame Jeſus, who was ſo reproachfully handled, and ſo barbarouſly crucified by the Jews, ſhould after his death be adored by Kings, and Emperours, and his Croſs an Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to Crowns and Scepters? When our moſt gracious Soveraign, who was ſo long depulſed from his Trone, diſcarded by his ſubjects, proſcribed out of the Land, ſhould at laſt be inſtalled Soveraign Lord over <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, God is able to ſet all things to rights again? and tho he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtands by and ſuffers wicked Men to act their pleaſure; yet after a while the counſel of the Lord that ſhall ſtand, which ought to be a ſupport and encouragement to all Governours, and a terrour to the obſtinate and Rebellious, for whether men will be obedient to them or not, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they diſcard and lay them aſide, or
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:102700:22"/>whatever they are pleaſed to do with them, yet Gods ends muſt be ſerved in the world, his Will ſhall be done <hi>be the Earth never ſo impatient;</hi> and that very <hi>Stone which the builders rejected,</hi> ſhall in his good time be made <hi>Head of the Corner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus diſpatcht the chief mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I deſigned at the beginning, I will only now give ſome ſhort and modeſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions upon the day, and ſo conclude.</p>
            <p>If all the Topicks that I have now ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for obedience unto the King and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment we live under, be not ſufficient, I hope the memory and experience of our late unhappy troubles will abundantly prevail upon the moſt ſtif necked amongſt us. Let any of our ſectaries look back and conſider the ſad poſture of affairs in the year 41. and recount, if they can, all the evils and miſchiefs that guſhed in upon the Nation during the Civil Wars. I ſay let any of them that ſurvived the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and had been for ſometime under the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:102700:22"/>hatches, confeſs if they would pay ſo dear for Rebellion once more; whether they could ever find in their hearts to ſet one foot towards the introducing again ſuch dolorous and bloody times in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; which I can parallel to nothing but a kind of <hi>Interregnum</hi> where after the death of the <hi>Alcade</hi> or chief Governour, the people are allowed to do all manner of villanies until another is choſen. Or to that ſad time among the Jews, <hi>when there was no King in Iſrael, in the which every man did that which was lawful and right in his own eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The old civilized Romans had ſuch an opinion of the auguſtneſs of their City, that to be proſcribed or baniſhed was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a capital puniſhment, and a civil death thought equal to a natural. O that I could perſwade all of you to be ſuch brave ſpirited Romans, and to have ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard for this Royal City, the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of our Nation, never to commit any baſe or diſloyal action as to merit proſcription from it, but be as conſtant and true to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:102700:23"/>King, as we are fully convinced the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of this place are, by this ſolemn an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſary Feſtival; and if ſeveral Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries heretofore ſtrove which ſhould have the honour of <hi>Homers</hi> birth, ſure it is no ſmall addition to our happineſs, ſeeing this very Pariſh is honoured with ſo good a Kings Nativity as well as ours: And if we enjoy not now all the rights and priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, which hath been long ſince continued to this our Imperial City, we may e'ne thank ſome of its Phariſaical members, who by their open Rebellions have for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited <hi>the great Seal and Charter of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray God then, we may all lay it to heart and let our Rebellion terminate here, and every man ſit down content, and <hi>eat the fruit of his labour under his own Vine, and under his own fig-Tree.</hi> For what can any expect by diſturbing and thwartning the Government, but abundance of evils and calamities muſt enſue; And then how deep will their guilt be, and what a great deal of blood muſt be Spilt, and how many lives loſt in ſuch wild heats and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:102700:23"/>combuſtions. <hi>Xerxes,</hi> when he beheld his army paſs before him, it drew tears from his eyes, that a hundred years hence there would not be a man of them left. Here was ſomething of good nature, but we ſtrive, as faſt as we can, by our fierce de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates and quarrellings to deſtroy and be the death of as many, and to imbrue our hands one in anothers blood.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſtrange and prepoſterous do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and very ill-timed, and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian breaches, and heartily to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and ſorrowed for, and do much weaken our Nation, and fit us for a final overthrow. I remember <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſayes, the unhappy diviſions that were among the <hi>Jews</hi> in the time of their Siege did more ſhake the foundations of their City than <hi>Titus</hi> his whole Army without the Walls. And in another place, he has moſt impartially related, that there was no care of Religion, no zeal for the Law amongſt them, becauſe there was nothing but bandings and factions in their Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues. And I am afraid that our zeal for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:102700:24"/>ſmall and indifferent matters, for circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials only, hath quite eaten up the very Spirit and life of our Religion; and well may we be bore down by the common enemy, when we do all we can by our deviliſh and inhumane breaches to prepare the way and accelerate his coming in.</p>
            <p>And beſides this, there is ſuch a ſurplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of Atheiſm and prophanneſs, of irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and ungodlineſs abounding every where, that notwithſtanding what <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venal</hi> remark long ago — <hi>omne in praeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piti vitium Stetit</hi> — all vice was at the height. Yet if it be poſſible the times we now live in are worſe; And albeit ſome would inſinuate, that it is the <hi>humour of every age to cry down their own times;</hi> yet iniquity is now grown ſo bare faced and rife in our ſtreets that there is not the leſt umbrage or colour for ſuch a pretext. And was there nothing more, his is enough to throw us out of the protection of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, and to make us the fag-end and refuſe of Gods Creation. For what ſaies <hi>Solomon, righteouſneſs exalteth a Nation but
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:102700:24"/>ſin is the reproach and confuſion of any peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> And to uſe the words of a great man, <q>the experience of every age has made this good: All along the hiſtory of the old Teſtament, we find the interchangeable providences of God towards the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> always ſuited to their manners; they were either proſperous or afflicted according as virtue and piety floriſhed or declined amongſt them. And God did not only exerciſe this Providence towards his own people, but he dealt thus with other Nations. The <hi>Roman</hi> Empire whilſt the virtue of that people continued firm, was ſtrong as iron as tis repreſented in the propheſie of <hi>Daniel,</hi> but upon the diſſolution of their manners the iron be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be mixt with miry clay, and the feet upon which the Empire ſtood to be broken in pieces.</q>
            </p>
            <p>No doubt than but it was our own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding guilt and ſinfulneſs that deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the nation, and plunged us into ſuch an abyſs of miſery and confuſion. But ſeeing this happy <hi>day</hi> hath given us a bleſſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:102700:25"/>to life again, and turned all our heavineſs into joy and rejoycing; <hi>O ſing therefore unto the Lord a new ſong, for he hath done marvellous things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 98.</note> 
               <hi>with his own right hand and with his holy arm hath he gotten himſelf the victory. Praiſe the Lord upon the harp, ſing to the harp with a Pſalm of thanksgiving; with trumpets and Shawms, O ſhew your ſelves joyful before the Lord the King. Let the ſea make a noiſe and all that there in is, the round world and they that dwell therein. Let the ſtoods clap their hands, and let the hills be joyful together before the Lord.</hi> For this Nation was ſunk deep into the earth, but now it hath lift up his head again. The people all lived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der bondage and thraldom, but now are at perfect liberty, and enjoy their own. Oppreſſion and Tyranny before infeſted the land, but now <hi>mercy and truth are met together, and righteouſneſs and peace have kiſſed each other.</hi> The hinges of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that were all disjonted and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, are now redintegrated, and turn up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame axle. Our moſt gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:102700:25"/>who had been ſo long baniſhed on a foreign ſhore is now landed again, and become the delight and glory of three Kingdoms: That very <hi>Sun</hi> which before was ſhrowded and ſet, is now ſtept from behind the cloud, and ſhines upon us with all his heavenly and benign influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences.</p>
            <p>In a word.</p>
            <p>Seeing this <hi>day</hi> then hath put a final period to all our grievences, Oh let us ſtudy to be peaceable and quiet, and not Phyſick our diſtemper to a worſe, but learn the leſſon of obedience better for the time to come, and mind the peace and proſperity of our Nation, and the preſervation of his Majeſties moſt ſacred Perſon, who after ſeveral years hazards and turmoils, by his own Country-men and by Foreigners; and after all thoſe attempts and offers that were made by the Prieſts while he was beyond ſea, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him from the true Religion, bleſſed be God, yea! thrice bleſſed be God, who preſerved him all along through the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:102700:26"/>and at length brought him back in the ſame faith and profeſſion as he went out. And let us all now implore the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of Gods mercy towards him, that his Reign may be long and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous and his years many; that he would bleſs him both in body and Soul, and give him the hearts and love of all his Subjects; that he would <hi>make him wiſe as an Angel of light,</hi> and a faithful Miniſter of juſtice among his people; that he would give him the victory over all his enemies, at home and abroad; and <hi>let them be driven back and put to confuſion that wiſh him evil;</hi> that he would <hi>ſet a Crown of pure gold upon his own head,</hi> and ſo make him for ever happy in this life, and when that diſmal night draweth near in which we muſt part with him, Crown him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſtingly in the world to come.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102700:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
